A Guide to the Papers of the Barbour Family 1793-1941
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Barbour Family, 1793-1941
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1486
This collection contains ca. 2,275 items (7 Hollinger boxes, ca. 3 linear shelf feet); oversize photograph and political cartoon.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The James Barbour Family Papers were purchased from Mrs. Caroline H. (Barbour) Ellis of Charlottesville, Virginia, on August 3, 1942.
Biographical/Historical Information
James Barbour (1775-1842) of Orange County, Virginia, was the son of Col. Thomas Barbour, who served in the House of Burgesses and on the committee of Safety during the Revolutionary War. James Barbour was a member of the General Assembly (1796-1812) until he became governor in 1812, serving during the tumultuous years of the War of 1812. Following the war, he was elected to the United States Senate and served from 1815-1825; he served as Secretary of War under President John Quincy Adams, 1825-1829. In 1829, he returned to his life as a Virginia planter, residing in "Barboursville."
His son, Benjamin Johnson Barbour (1821-1894), attended the University of Virginia from 1837-1839. After the conclusion of the Civil War, Barbour was appointed by Governor Pierpoint to the new Board of Visitors (1865-1873). He served as Rector from 1866 until 1872.
Barbour belonged to the old Whig party of Virginia and was the orator at the unveiling of the Henry Clay statue in Capitol Square, Richmond, in 1858. It was said that he never approved of the secession of Virginia from the Union But after the beginning of hostilities at Ft. Sumter, he suggested that a subscription be made for the defense of the state. In 1865 he was elected to Congress but was not seated. He did serve in the House of Delegates from 1879 to 1880. Barbour also served as a visitor to the Miller School in Albermarle County, was prominent in the State Agriculture Society, and was president of the University of Virginia Alumni Society.
Genealogical Appendix
I. James Barbour (1775-1842) m. (1795) Lucy Johnson (1775-1860)
Their children:
1) Lucy Maria (Barbour) Taliferro (1797-1843)
2) James Barbour (1798-1857)
3) B. Johnson Barbour, 1st (1802-1820)
4) Frances Cornelia Barbour, 1st (1801-1802)
5) Frances Cornelia (Barbour) Collins, (1812-1893)
6) Phillip Pendleton Barbour (1816- )
7) B. Johnson Barbour, 2nd (1821-1894)
II. B Johnson Barbour (1821-1894) m. (1844) Caroline H. Watson (1825-1905)
Their children:
1) James Barbour (1846-1851)
2) Anne Watson Barbour (1847-1851)
3) George Watson Barbour, 1st (1849-1858)
4) B. Johnson Barbour, Jr. (1851-1853)
5) Thomas Barbour (1854-1938)
6) Lucy C. Barbour (1856-1863)
7) George Watson Barbour, 2nd (1859- 1937)
8) Caroline H. (Barbour) Ellis (1861-1943 ?)
9) William C. Barbour (1865d.) 10) Elise Collins (Barbour) Graves (1865- ?)
11) Frances Cornelia (Barbour) Christian (1870- 1940)
Scope and Content Information
This collection chiefly consists of the personal and financial papers of James Barbour (1775-1842) of "Barboursville," Orange County, Virginia, and his descendants. The collection contains financial and legal papers, printed material, correspondence, scrapbooks, plats, manuscripts, commonplace books, genealogical information, drawings, ballot sheets, Union Army general orders from the Civil War, and slave inventories.
The correspondence and financial papers of James Barbour, his son, Benjamin Johnson Barbour (1821-1894), and his granddaughter, Caroline Homassel Barbour Ellis (1861- ) form the bulk of the collection. The collection does not contain any official papers from James Barbour's service in the U. S. Senate, in the national government, or as governor of Virginia. The papers of Benjamin Johnson Barbour contain much correspondence from his association with the University of Virginia as a member of the Board of Visitors and Rector. The letters of most of the correspondents, whose names are listed later in this guide, can be found in his personal correspondence.
Topics of interest in the letters include: James Barbour's complaints concerning his son James' extravagance while attending Harvard, and references to hardships during the War of 1812 (October 19, 1815; July 25, 1816); slaves and slavery (September 2, 1822; May 22, 1824); Barbour family genealogy (February 7, 1829; January 18 and 28, August 24, November 21, 1885; April 14, 1893; December 3 and 24, 1900; May 28, 1917); B. Johnson Barbour's summary of his letter to W. D. Blair discussing whether the American Party opposed the election of Roman Catholics to political office and a discussion of the importance of Reformation (January 25, 1855); rail travel from Virginia to Florida, and the importance of cotton, (February 11, 1857); plans for the construction of the Orange County courthouse (February 25, July 14, and 16, 1858); Alexander Rives' urging of B. J. Barbour to side publicly with the Union men of the state and to enter the Republican ranks during the August Convention (July 10, 1867); Robert Bolling's urging of B. J. Barbour and other conservatives to support the Republican Party which "saved the Union," and to ignore the "bugbear" of "Negro supremacy" (May 12, 1868); appointment of B. J. Barbour to the Board of Visitors of the United States Military Academy (May 28, 1866); an invitation to attend an organizational meeting for the Immigration Society to encourage immigration to Virginia (May 28, 1867); presence of Dr. Archer at Ft. King in 1835 when Osceola shot General Wiley Thompson (June 7, 1877); Miller fund (April 26, 1883); political activities of William Mahone (October 26, 1885), C. H. Fauntleroy's discussion of his law practice in St. Paul, Minnesota, among German-speaking clients (April 14, 1886), a description of St. Paul (May 31, 1886) and the Minneapolis Exposition (August 23, 1886); Daniel Wolsey Voorhees (1827-1897) regarding passage of his bill for the Library of Congress building (May 7, 1886); Governor Fitzhugh Lee (January 20, May 18, November 14, 1887); Thomas L. Rosser regarding politics (July 15 and December 4, 1888); A. G. Grinnan regarding a story of how some James Madison letters were used by the gardener to mulch grape vines ([1889]); W. Gordon McCabe regarding extracts from Gazeta Polska and affairs in Poland and Russia (January 28, 1889), orations of James Barbour (July 9, 1890), and literary matters (March 3, 1891); race relations (February 6, 1891); the Boer War (March 4, 1900); description of the Great Earthquake in California, 1906 (May 1, 1906); Robert Frost reading his poetry at Littleton, New Hampshire (August 12, 1917); a description of festivities at the Yorktown Sesquicentennial celebration (October 27, 1931).
Because B. Johnson Barbour served as Rector of the University of Virgina, a large quantity of his correspondence concerns the University and its faculty. It includes the following: W. E. Peter's acceptance of the Latin professorship (September 13, 1866); Charles Venable on establishing a certificate for mathematics (June 10, 1867); J. L. Cabell regarding the student Infirmary Fund (November 15, 1867); J. H. Mckinne about Washington Hall (March 23, 1869); F. H. Smith on astronomical observations (April 12, 1869); Alexander J. Davis's questions about renovations or additions to the buildings (May 6, 1869); J. W. Mallet on an agricultural department (January 16 and February 11, 1870); Stephen Southall on the use of the office of rector as a political office, and the detrimental effect of politics on the welfare of the University (January 15, 1884); Charles Venable about selling the Lee Family Papers to the Library of Congress and estblishing a Lee Donation (July 14, 1886); condition of the reservoir dam that supplied the University with water (July 30, 1886); John L. Marye on the reorganization of the four schools of Dr. Page, Dr. Garnett, Dr. Holmes, and Dr. Schele de Vere (February 4, April 13, and June 6, 1887); F. H. Smith on having the University's bell recast and placed in the chapel (March 7, 1887 and March 7, 1889); C. H. Fauntleroy on the resignation of John R. Page and C. Venable's possessiveness of the University (May 30, 1887) and the resignation of Dr. Harrison and the discussion of his supposed affair, and denunciation of the Presbyterian influence at the University (July 2 and 9, 1887); and M. A. Turner's description and opinion of French, German, and Italian naval officers (n.d.).
Other general topics include: literary discussions, agricultural science, family news, Virginia politics, Reconstruction policies, involvement in Red Cross work for Orange County and Garden Week, and the disposition of papers of James Barbour.
Other frequent or notable correspondents include: Stephen Adams (1835-?), John Anderson, Parker E. Bagby, John Strode Barbour (1820-1892), T. F. Bayard, William Beckner, William M. Blackford (1801-1864), Robert Bolling, Frank Brown, Charles Page Bryan (1856-1918), J. L. Cabell, Mary Cameron, W. G. Christian (1862- ), R. L. Combs, William C. Dabney (1849-1894), N. M. Duke, the Rev. Josiah Richard Ellis, Lily Ellis, Dr. Thomas Harding Ellis (? -1914), Cornelius Hite Fauntleroy (1859-1921), Judge Thomas T. Fauntleroy (1823-1906), I. T. Frary, James Mercer Garnett (1840-1916), J. C. Gibson, Basil L. Gildersleeve (1831-1924), James Lindsay Gordon (1860-1904), J. C. Graves, Nannie Ellis Hall, Randolph Harrison (1857-1928), Barton Haxall (1856-?), Burton W. Haxall, George F. Holmes (1820-1897), Robert Wilson Hughes (1821-1901), Eppa Hunton (1822-1908), Arthur J., Horace G. and Sadie Lindsay (Patton) Hutchinson, Wyndham Kemp, James Lawson Kemper (1824-1878), Fitzhugh Lee (1835-1905), Thomas Lee, John H. Lewis (1841-1907), Hiram Liggett, William Gordon McCabe (1841-1920), Leander James McCormick (1819-1900), [Clement] P. and J. H. McKennie, William Mahone, Jr. (1826-1895), John William Mallet (1832-1912), John Lawrence Marye (1823-?), John Edward Massey (1819-1901), Beatrice Mayer, John B. Minor (1813-1895), John R. Page (1830-1901), Fanny K. Patton, William Henry Payne (1830-1904), Edmund and J. D. Pendleton, William E. Peters (1829-1906), Wilson Cary Nicholas Randolph (1834-1907), Alexander Rives (1806-1885), Thomas L. Rosser (1836-1910), Frank G. Ruffin (1816-1892), Maximilian Schele de Vere (1820-1898), Wallace W. Scott, Virginius Shackelford (1885-1949), Lucy L. Slaughter, Francis H. Smith (1829-1928), F. W. and Stephen Osborne Southall (1816-1884), Edwin M. Stanton (1814-1869), Ormond Stone (1847-1933), Taliaferro family, Glanville Terrell (1859-1936), W. B. Towles, Mortimer Turner, Charles Venable (1827-1906), Rueben Lindsay Walker (1827-1890), John H. Wheeler, John Wickam, and John S. Wise (1846-1913).
Family correspondents include: Benjamin Johnson Barbour, Caroline H. (Watson) Barbour, Carry H. (Barbour) Ellis, Frances Cornelia (Barbour) Christian, Elise Collins (Barbour) Graves, James Barbour, Jr., Lucy Barbour, George Watson Barbour, and Thomas Barbour.
Other items of interest include: ballot sheets for the election of Zachary Taylor (1848); an original political cartoon about William Henry Harrison's (1773-1841) presidential campaign (ca. 1840); Resolutions of the Board of Visitors, University of Virginia, on salaries of professors (1850-1865); copies of general orders issued by General Banks and McClellan, U. S. Army of the Potomac, August-November 1861; minutes of membership list (1876-1879) of the Lay Association of the Protestant Episcopal Church, Diocese of Virginia; minutes, 1892, of the Society of Alumni of the University of Virginia; undated photographs of "Barboursville"; and slave inventories (bound volumes, 1803-1822 and 1854).
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged chronologically by type of material, except for the bound volumes. These have been placed at the end of the collection.
Contents List
- Accounts, bills receipts and bonds 1793-1810 (Box 1)
- Thomas Davison to James Barbour February 24, 1812, ALS (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts and bonds of James Barbour 1812-1818 (Box 1)
- Indenture of James Barbour June 4, 1813 (Box 1)
- James Barbour to his son, James Barbour, Jr. and Henry Hovey to James Barbour, Jr. 1815-1816, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Notebook containing legal notes of James Barbour, Jr. and Henry Hovey to James Barbour, Jr. 1819, AMs and ALs (Box 1)
- Peter Johnson to James Barbour and Josiah B. Abbott to James Barbour September 2, 1822 and May 22, 1824 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1820-1825 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of James Barbour 1826-1829 (Box 1)
- John Riddell to James Barbour re Barbour genealogy February 7, 1829 (Box 1)
- Poem, "Weep No More" by [James Barbour] and an untitled poem [1829] (Box 1)
- Correspondence of James Barbour re business matters 1830-1835 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of James Barbour 1830-1839 (Box 1)
- Speech of Mr. Webster in the Senate, in reply to Mr. Calhoun's Speech... (printed copy) February 16, 1833 (Box 1)
- "A Discourse on Sin and Its Cure" by Elder A. Rains May 1835 (Box 1)
- Land Grant in Florida Territory to James Barbour October 20, 1835 (Box 1)
- Account book 1839-1842 (Box 1)
- Letters to James Barbour 1840-1842 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1840-1844 (Box 1)
- B. Johnsn Barbour to Caroline H. Watson and one letter, Lucy Barbour to C. H. Watson [1844] (Box 1)
- B. Johnson Barbour to Caroline H. Watson August 11, 1844 and October 12, 1844, 2 ALS (Box 1)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1845-1846, 3 ALS (Box 1)
- Architectural Drawing for Commanders' House, site 34, Navy Yard, Kittery, Maine September 20, 1848 (Box 1)
- Letters to James Barbour, Jr. 1848 (Box 1)
- Ballot Sheets for election of Zachary Taylor November 7, 1848 (Box 1)
- Pamphlet: The Agricultural Advertiser 1849 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of B. Johnson Barbour 1849-1858 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1850-1858 (Box 1)
- Resolutions of the Board of Visitors, University of Virginia, re the salaries of professors June 28, 1850 - July 5, 1865 (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Barbour family 1852-1867 (Box 1)
- Power of Attorney of Benjamin Johnson Barbour for Frances Cornelia Taliaferro, Ann Baird Taliaferro and Sarah Lindsay Taliaferro January 22, 1857 (Box 1)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1860-1868 (Box 1)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1860-1869 (Box 1)
- General Orders 1861 (Box 1)
- Statement of fees for each school of the University of Virginia and a draft of a report made by the Rector re the University to the Governor of Virginia, Gilbert C. Walker 1865-1870 (Box 1)
- Account book of B. Johnson Barbour, including Miscellaneous notes 1866-1883 (Box 2)
- Letters of B. Johnson Barbour, chiefly as Rector of the University of Virginia 1869-1875 (Box 2)
- "Removal of Political Disabilities" a speech of Hon. Anthony A. C. Rogers of Arkansas February 21, 1870 (Box 2)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1870-1885 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of Thomas Barbour 1871-1878 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of B. Johnson Barbour 1876-1885 (Box 2)
- Lay Association of the Protstant Episcopal Church, Diocese of Virginia, Minutes and Membership List 1876-1879 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Barbour family 1877-1890 (Box 2)
- 2 Broadsides advertising the public sale of land and livestock belonging to B. Johnson Barbour in Orange County, Va. 1877 (Box 2)
- Printed Material of the Barbour Family 1881-1889 (Box 2)
- Plats of land purchased from B. Johnson Barbour by the Virginia Midland Railway for a depot 1882 (Box 2)
- Biographical Sketch of the Hon. William Cabell Carrington [1885] and April 11, 1885 (Box 2)
- Legal documents of the Barbour family 1885-1889 (Box 2)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1886 (Box 2)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1887 (Box 2)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1888-1889 (Box 2)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family 1888-1889 (Box 2)
- Map of land in Albemarle County owned by B. Johnson Barbour 189- (Box 2)
- Letters to B. Johnson Barbour 1890-1894 (Box 2)
- Society of Alumni of University of Virginia Minutes June 29, 1892 (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Barbour family 1892-1899 (Box 3)
- Letters to the Barbour family expressing sympathy at the death of B. Johnson Barbour 1894-1895 n.d. (Box 3)
- Letters from Caroline Watson Barbour to Caroline Barbour Ellis 1895-1896 (Box 3)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Ellis family 1895-1940 (Box 3)
- Human hair May 5, 1897 and n.d. (Box 3)
- Letters from Caroline Watson Barbour to Caroline Barbour Ellis 1897-1900 n.d. (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Printed (Box 3)
- Correspondence of the Ellis family 1900-1914 (Box 3)
- Letters to Caroline Ellis expressing sympathy at the death of her mother, Caroline Barbour 1904 (Box 4)
- Letters to Caroline Ellis while a patient at Martha Jefferson Hospital 1911 (Box 4)
- Letters to Caroline Ellis 1915-1919 (Box 4)
- Letters to Caroline Ellis 1920-1930 (Box 4)
- Letters to Caroline Ellis 1931-1940 (Box 4)
- Photographs, postcards, and a coat of arms 1873-1931 (Box 4)
- Accounts, bills, receipts, etc. of the Barbour family n.d. (Box 4)
- Genealogical Notes n.d. (Box 4)
- Photographs of "Barboursville" n.d. (Box 4)
- Correspondence of the Barbour family n.d. (Box 5)
- Correspondence of the Ellis family n.d. (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous Poetry and other Maunuscripts n.d. (Box 5)
- "List of Letters from Celebrated Men" n.d. (Box 5)
- Notebooks 1888-1935 (Box 5)
- Day Book 1824-1828, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Account Book 1884-1885, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Memorandum Book 1874, Bound Volume (Box 1874)
- [W.] A. Stephens Compass Notes Powell's Gap (1847), Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Personal Account Book (1909), Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Memorandum Book and Diary (1829-1833), Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Memorandum Book of B. Johnson Barbour 1858, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Cashbook (1828-1840), Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Memorandum and Notebook re Politics kept by B. J. Barbour 1880, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Commonplace Book kept by James Barbour Taliaferro n.d., Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Commonplace and Cash Book 1816-1825, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Red Cross Record Book 1918, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Inventory of Slaves for 1854 and brief diary of [Carry Barbour] 1880-1881, Bound Volume (Box 5)
- Scrapbook 1890-1895, Bound Volume (Box 6)
- Scrapbook 1881-1917, Bound Volume (Box 6)
- Account book including a list of slaves and real estate 1803-1822, Bound Volume (Box 6)
- Account book re estate of Col. Benjamine Johnson 1801-1806, Bound Volume (Box 6)
- Account Book 1828-1866, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Account Book 1822-1823, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- 1907 Meteorological Record Sheets 1907, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Day Book for Barbour and Johnson 1785-1786, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Agricultural Journal w/partial ledger of Gov. James Barbour, including genealogical notes 1811-1941, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Scrapbook 1851-1900, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Cashbook 1841-1881, Bound Volume (Box 7)
- Photograph of James Barbour (1775-1842), Oversize
- Political Cartoon re Presidential Campaign of 1840 (1775-1842), Oversize